A Guide to the Collection Regarding Oliver Cromwell, 1640-1970
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Collection Regarding Oliver Cromwell, 1640-1970
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5368, -a-d
This collection consists of 700 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Charles C. Abbott of Pomfret Center, Connecticut, through the Rare Book Division on five different occasions: #5368, November 29, 1973; #5368-a, August 21, 1974; #5368-b, April 18, 1980; #5368-c, April 18, 1980; and, #5368-d, August 13, 1980.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 700 items, 16th to 20th centuries, primarily engravings, prints, drawings, magazine photographs, and modern reproductions depicting Oliver Cromwell. In addition, there are prints of Cromwell's contemporaries, battle scenes, and group pictures in which Cromwell appears, and town views and maps from Cromwell's periods. Several legal documents, 1642-1659; photocopies and transcript of manuscripts; newspaper clippings, 1841-1934; and an indexed scrapbook, 1837-1849, of newspaper clippings, all concerning Cromwell, are also present. A list of engravers of portraits of Cromwell and a plaster cast of a death mask of Cromwell complete the collection.
Contents List
- Engravings, book jackets, etc. of Oliver Cromwell 1653-1915, n.d., Topical. 142 items, 2 folders.
- Reproductions of engravings of portraits of Oliver Cromwell n.d., Topical. 59 items.
- Engravings of some of Cromwell's contemporaries; maps of England, Scotland, and Wales; and miscellaneous subjects 1784-1866, n.d., Topical. 44 items.
- Documents re Oliver Cromwell, including three Cromwell autographs (one facsimile) and one Richard Cromwell autograph 1642-1659, Topical. 6 items.
- Reproductions from books (1649, 1659) re Oliver Cromwell n.d., Topical. 4 items.
- List of engravers of portraits of Cromwell n.d., Topical. 1 item.
- Cromwell manuscripts 1655, n.d., Topical. Transcripts. 3 items.
- Manuscripts re Cromwell 1643-1657, Topical. Photocopies. 16 items.
- Notes re Cromwell 1827, n.d., Topical. 24 items. 8 items.
- Newspaper clippings re Oliver Cromwell 1841-1934, n.d., Topical. 24 items.
- Catalogues of British and foreign portraits for sale 1838, Topical. 3 items.
- Evered & Company to Messrs. Cox & Sons re order for two desk rail pillars 1907 June 4, Topical. Letter (TLS).
- Index to Scrapbook [1854], Topical.
- Scrapbook of newspaper clippings re Oliver Cromwell 1837-1849, Bound Volumes
- Indenture between Oliver Cromwell and Edward Eserbert 1651 Oct 1, Oversize Items
- Oliver Cromwell's answer to a petition of the East India Company for a naval convoy for their ships from India 1657 Nov 6, Oversize Items. Negative photocopy.
- Legal document granting John Sumpner custody of William Copley by Richard Cromwell 1659 Mar 9, Oversize Items
- Legal documents n.d., Oversize Items. Photocopy. 2 items.
- Engravings, prints, drawings, reproductions, etc. of Oliver Cromwell and his contemporaries ca. 1650-1970, Oversize Items. 450 items.